<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of S'hertogenbosh: vvritten in the yeere 1540, by Simon Pelgrom of S'hertogenbosh, in his life time prior and prouinciall of the order of Guilhelmines. Together with the principall points and passages concerning the last siege. Also, a register from day to day, of that which hath happened, aswell without as within the towne, from the first beginning vntill the latter end of the said siege. Translated out of the Dutch tongue, and printed according to the originall</title>
            <author>Pelegromius, Simon, 1507?-1572.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09242</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19555</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114369</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849595</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849595</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14752</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09242)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14752)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 969:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of S'hertogenbosh: vvritten in the yeere 1540, by Simon Pelgrom of S'hertogenbosh, in his life time prior and prouinciall of the order of Guilhelmines. Together with the principall points and passages concerning the last siege. Also, a register from day to day, of that which hath happened, aswell without as within the towne, from the first beginning vntill the latter end of the said siege. Translated out of the Dutch tongue, and printed according to the originall</title>
                  <author>Pelegromius, Simon, 1507?-1572.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 52, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by George Purslowe] for Nicholas Bourne, dwelling at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1629.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dutch original not traced.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>'s Hertogenbosch (Netherlands : Meierij)) --  History --  Siege, 1629 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14752:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14752:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DESCRIPTION OF S'HERTOGENBOSH: VVritten in the yeere 1540, by <hi>Simon Pelgrom</hi> of S'<hi>hertogenboſh,</hi> in his life time Prior and Prouinciall of the Order of <hi>Guilhelmines.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with <hi>The principall points and paſſages</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the laſt Siege.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>ALSO,</hi> A Regiſter from day to day, of that which hath happened, aſwell without as within the Towne, from the firſt beginning vntill the latter end of the ſaid Siege.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of the</hi> Dutch <hi>Tongue, and printed according to the Originall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Nicholas Bourne,</hi> dwelling at the South entrance of the Royall Exchange 1629.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="description">
            <pb facs="tcp:14752:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14752:2"/>
            <head>A Deſcription of <hi>S'hertogenboſh:</hi> Written in the Yeere 1540.</head>
            <head type="sub">Together with a Regiſter of all the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall paſſages in the late ſiege of the ſaid Towne, 1629.</head>
            <head>Vnto the Worthy, Worſhipfull, and Diſcreete Lords, Chiefe Baily, Preſidext, Sheriffes, and Councellours of the renowned Towne of <hi>S'herto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genboſh.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe place whereupon the Towne of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> is built, hath heeretofore (according to the common preſumption) beene a Boſcage or Wood, kept for the Hunting of the Dukes of <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant;</hi> of this Boſcage the Towne hath the name of <hi>S'hertogenboſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Boſcage was an euen and recreatiue place, fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of wild Deere, as of Harts, Hinds, Wilde Bores, Wolues, Hares, Rabbets, and ſuch like: wherein were many little water-brookes, Orchards, and Hearbes.</p>
            <p>In this Boſcage the Duke had made a Cottage, as-well for his Dogges and Horſes, when he went a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, as alſo for men to be at ſhelter from the raine and
<pb facs="tcp:14752:3"/>great heate. This ſame Cottage was after this named the <hi>Hanſe-wint,</hi> or in Engliſh the <hi>Grayhound,</hi> and is yet vpon the Market-place.</p>
            <p>The Hunters of the Duke had made a Ditch round about this Hutte, for to be aſſured againſt the forces of their Enemies; becauſe there was a great difference riſen betweene them and the Hunters of the Count of <hi>Meghen,</hi> for that they were come vnder the Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the ſaid Count, following not onely their Dogges that were aſtray, but alſo by reaſon of the great heate, their Game. Wherefore they were very much beaten and hurt by the Counts Hunters, for da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to hunt in anothers Hunting place. The Duke tooke this very ill ſo that he forced thoſe of <hi>Meghen</hi> to hang thoſe dead Dogs by the hinder legs on high, and for reparation of their fault, to couer them with Corne.</p>
            <p>The place of this Boſcage was fit for many vſes, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing in the middeſt a common Riuer, where reſorted (as if it had been a common Hauen) many men, there to receiue their goods which they had bought.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Kempenlanders, Peelanders,</hi> and their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, were wont to bring their Bees towards the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theſt dominions of <hi>Gelder,</hi> for that that Land hath a ſweet ayre, and was very fruitfull of Corne, Bloſſoms, Ypes, or Broomes bloſſomes, being very good foode for the Bees. This Nation bringing ouer their Bees in Hiues, and trading with the <hi>Gelders</hi> Nation for Corne. Beanes, Peaſe, Cheeſe, and ſuch like Wares, they haue choſen this place as the fitteſt, where they came in great number with their Boars, and Carres: for to receiue thoſe Wares they daily bought. And it hapned then that this place, by reaſon of the great trading more and more did encreaſe, wherefore ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny came thither.</p>
            <p>There were then no publike Tauernes for to lodge
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14752:3"/>the Iourneying Trauellor, ſo that they were forced to lye in the Field, vnleſſe they would goe to the next Villages and Houſes. A certaine Trauellour, being weary of this miſery, was minded there to build, and was the firſt that builded there a Publike Tauerne, neere the old <hi>Dieſe,</hi> about the <hi>Geertruyde</hi>-Bridge, who was, by reaſon of the many Gueſts, and good trading, in a ſhort time growne very rich: which was no wonder, becauſe it was then a peaceable time, and the people came there in great number, as well from the <hi>Gelder</hi> quarters, principally from <hi>Bonuneler, Tielerweert, Maes,</hi> and <hi>Wael,</hi> as alſo out of the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Brabant,</hi> namely, from <hi>Bruſſels, Louen, Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werpe, Kempenland,</hi> and out of all the Townes and places ſituated there round about, for to trade with their Merchandiſe in this place.</p>
            <p>By reaſon of this good ſucceſſe and welfare of this Vintner, (like men being of nature artificers) there came more yet to build their dwelling-places there: ſo that there were built many Houſes. Theſe then were the firſt luckie beginners of the Towne to come.</p>
            <p>Euen as thoſe that proſper are hated, miſery onely is freed, ſo the proſperity of this people hath beene hated by the Burgers of <hi>Heuſden,</hi> becauſe this Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and Merchandiſe was wont to bee with them. Theſe Burgers then fearing that ſuch a luckie begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and great multiplication of theſe new buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſhould doe them not ſmall, but very great hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance, and that their Towne, for want of men and trading, would come to nothing: therefore they thought how to preuent it, and by what meanes they might beſt hinder it. After they had well medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated theſe buſineſſes, and iudging, that their lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger ſtaying would bee but a hinderance vnto them, they concluded together to fall vpon theſe new
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14752:4"/>Builders, and cauſed them to depart: who hauing gotten fit opportunity, they did fall very ſecretly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, cauſed them to depart out of the place, and beate downe their new Buildings to the very ground, for to hinder theſe ſpeedy beginnings; which otherwiſe would haue put downe all the trading of their Towne.</p>
            <p>This attempt was to no purpoſe againſt the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune: for that the people did not forſake this place by reaſon of the ſaid dammage and hinderance, but ſhortly after this returned thither againe, and did build againe new houſes in the old Field: for which the iealouſie of the Burgers of <hi>Heuſden</hi> did increaſe more and more, and would not leaue them at quiet, but fell for the ſecond time againe vpon them, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their houſes, and cauſed them to retire a great way off that place, to the end that their laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſhould not bee greater then the firſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe people being twice deſtroyed and ruined by the Burgers of <hi>Heuſden,</hi> they were forced to be ſtrag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glers here and there, which did grieue them much, hauing no meanes to reſiſt them; yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding continued ſtill in their opinions, and did looke alwaies for a better occaſion, hauing in minde the ſaying of the Poet <hi>Virgil:</hi>
            </p>
            <q>O paſsi grauiora dabit Deus his quoque finem.</q>
            <q>
               <l>On friends: let greater perrits paſt</l>
               <l>Giue greater Courage now at laſt;</l>
               <l>And God (who doth all what he wills)</l>
               <l>Will ſet a period to theſe ills.</l>
            </q>
            <p>And expecting after darkneſſe the light, were min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſeeke other helpe and aſsiſtance: They made their complaints vnto the Duke of <hi>Brabant,</hi> who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14752:4"/>(they knew) would aſsiſt thoſe that were in miſery; and manifeſted alſo their cauſe vnto the Burgers of the <hi>Brabandiſh</hi> head Towns, and did together require helpe and aſsiſtance, that they might bee aſſured a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the forces of thoſe of <hi>Heuſden,</hi> and to be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in their former place, that they might build vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine their pillaged and ruined Houſes.</p>
            <p>In this they were not deceiued of their hope, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe theſe <hi>Brabandiſh</hi> Burgers, hauing regard vnto their requeſt, condiſcended vnto them, and promiſed truely to helpe and aſsiſt them, ſo that hereafter they ſhould not any more bee hindred of their good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
            <p>The Illuſtrious Prince alledged this reaſon in the common Aſſembly, That he was willing to prouide vnto the ſame for time to come, but that he was now much troubled himſelfe with Warres, and great af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires, and therefore did put the ſaid cauſe to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the <hi>Brabandiſh</hi> Burgers.</p>
            <p>The three chiefe Townes of <hi>Braband,</hi> namely, <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, Bruſſels,</hi> and <hi>Antwerpe,</hi> tooke this Cauſe in good earneſt vpon them, and conſidering well of it, they found fit to build there the fourth chiefe Towne, to the end that the <hi>Brabanders</hi> forces might lye vpon 4. Pillers.</p>
            <p>By the command of the Prince, they began there to make there three Ports or Cates in a round, which were ended in a ſhort time: each chiefe Towne buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one Gate. Thoſe of <hi>Louen</hi> about the Market place, neere the great Hoſpitall, which is now the Priſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate. Thoſe of <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the Croſſe-gate, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maines ſtill in <hi>Orten-ſtreet.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Antwerpe</hi> the <hi>Vrouwe-port,</hi> or Gate, about the <hi>Wilde Bore,</hi> which in the augmentation of the Towne, was taken away by the Burgers.</p>
            <p>The Forces were made in fauour of theſe new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14752:5"/>becauſe that their Enemies and haters ſhould no more in time come to ſpoile nor ruine their building, nor to make them retire any more.</p>
            <p>Theſe chiefe Townes were ſpecially minded here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, to the end that the <hi>Gelders</hi> might be forced to ſtay in their Dominions<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for that the <hi>Brabanders</hi> moſt times were forced to maintaine Wars againſt them, about whoſe frontiers, the Townes, Villages, Houſes, and goods of the <hi>Brabanders</hi> are ſituated, which were ſtill very much ſpoiled and ruined by this <hi>Gelder</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Theſe then haue beene the beginnings of the new Towne, and the firſt foundations.</p>
            <p>When theſe Gates, in manner aforeſaid, were built ſo freely, there came ſo great a quantity of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to build and dwell therein as if vnder the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions there had beene Mines of Siluer.</p>
            <p>Theſe new Inhabitants taking anew their courage, which they had loſt by reaſon of the pillaging and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of thoſe of <hi>Heuſden<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> they builded againe new buildings, ſetting the Houſes one cloſe to the other, and the number of the ſame encreaſed daily more and more, and ſo faſt, that they at laſt, with the aſsiſtance of the Prince, did make a Wall and Ditch round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Towne, and ſtrengthned it with a ſtone wall, ſo that they were able to reſiſt their enemies.</p>
            <p>As the number of the comming Strangers did very much increaſe, and the Towne proſpered, ſo they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to build other new buildings.</p>
            <p>The Princes Court was the principall, and moſt coſtly builded, ſituated ouer againſt the Butchers Hall, where there is now the Tauerne called the <hi>Swanne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Houſe <hi>Rood enburgh</hi> is alſo built by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth for the gracing of the new Towne, and it was a great while the Treaſure-houſe of the towne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:14752:5"/>
The Towne-houſe was built as well at the charges of the Prince, as alſo of the Burgers.</p>
            <p>The Burgers of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> being come in ſuch a wiſhed ſtate, began to ſtatute Lawes, and to make a Magiſtrate, to bring the Riuer through the Towne, to make new ſtreets and wayes, and to make much one of another, wherefore they haue gotten great Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their Prince, as by the Letters thereof more at large may appeare.</p>
            <p>All thoſe that come to dwell there, although they were broken and Bankrupts, they got liberty of the Prince, wherefore it did happen, that there came ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny out of the Land of <hi>Cleefe, Guilicker-land, Gelder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and out of other neighbour places, to take their reſidence there.</p>
            <p>This ſaid Prouince yeeldeth very ſtrong and bold Women, ſo that theſe Strangers brought with them very bold Women, which for the moſt part had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand ouer their Husbands, and did make away the common goods in deſpight of their Husbands: Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Prince gaue vnto this Towne this Law, That the Women without their Husbands may not diſpoſe of any of their goods: but that the Husband, without the knowledge of the Woman, hath full power to ſell and diſpoſe of their goods.</p>
            <p>There were not as yet any Churches built in the new towne, but the <hi>Orten-Church,</hi> ſituated neere the <hi>Dieſe,</hi> hath beene a great while the Pariſh Church, which was long before built by a Gentleman, who being ſtrayed by the tempeſt of the Sea, landed there firſt of all; for that the Sea was wont to come in that place, as appeareth by the name of that place, called <hi>Ooort-Duyuen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There were alſo no Cloifters in the towne, the Fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were the firſt that began to build there, and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a ſmall dwelling houſe; after this they tooke a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14752:6"/>bigger place neere the Princes Court, and enlarged their place of reſidence, after the manner of Cellekins, and they haue alſo built a Church, which the Burgers haue vſed a great while for their Pariſh Church They were not yet tyed to any publike promiſes.</p>
            <p>Shortly after this there came many men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men from ſeuerall Regions in the ſame towne, after beginning of this towne, (as hereafter more at large ſhall be declared) they haue built there their Houſes and Cloyſters.</p>
            <p>The Towne was in a ſhort time ſo increaſed by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the louing and friendly Burgers, that euery one thought it ſhould haue been a ſecond <hi>Rome,</hi> and were forced becauſe of the multitude of men, to inlarge the Towne, and make it bigger, that the multitude of the Burgers might the better dwell therein.</p>
            <p>In the yeere 1300, when the augmentation of the towne was intended to be inlarged, the ſaid towne was therein aſsiſted by the Prince, and by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince of <hi>Brabant.</hi> The Burgers did make new Stee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in the precinct, with new Gates, they did alſo make new and wide ditches, and new Walles, and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained new Streets to be made; they brought the Riuer the <hi>Dommel,</hi> and the <hi>Aa</hi> in ſeuerall places tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Towne, and prouided further all that which was needfull for the augmentation of the Towne.</p>
            <p>This new towne was preſently multiplyed with new Burgers, which according to their ſtate, builded each for their commodity new houſes: and did ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in riches, as if they had got to the riches of <hi>Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus;</hi> by which meanes it happened, that there were built ſo many faire and coſtly Cloyſters, holy Houſes, and coſtly buildings, ſo that the moſt part of the new towne, is built with Cloyſters, Churches, Chappels, and ſuch like Houſes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:14752:6"/>
In the yeere 1380. there were laid the foundation of the great and renowned Church called S<hi rend="sup">t.</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> Church, the ground-place of which, together with the ſtreets ſituated there round about, from the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner-gate to the <hi>Hintemer</hi>-gate, is called the <hi>Hinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſant,</hi> becauſe the ſaid place heretofore hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained vnder the Vilage <hi>Hintem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>About that time there were built ſeuerall publike and priuate Houſes, as holy Churches, Hoſpitals, and diuers Houſes for the poore, which daily increaſed by reaſon of the riches of the Burgers, and their liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. Which things ſeuerall to declare, ſhould bee too long, and needleſſe.</p>
            <p>Theſe Burgers are, by reaſon of their ciuill carriage, wiſdome, and courteſie, come in great fauour vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one, being faithfull to euery one and did deceiue no body, neither were chargeable vnto any: Their friends were welcome vnto them, but they did reſiſt their enemies: for as the vnquiet and vnpeaceable <hi>Gelder</hi> Nation, when they were about the building of <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> did ſpoile the <hi>Brabandiſh</hi> Townes and Villages, ſetting on fire their Countrey-houſes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying their Lands, taking away their Horſes and Beaſts, and ruining all that whereby they could come; Likewiſe they (ſome while before the building of the Towne) did fall vpon the Village called <hi>Ooſterwicke,</hi> neere the Towne, and haue quite pillaged the ſame, and ſet on fire all the trees: Theſe Burgers of <hi>S'herto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genboſh</hi> haue after that, with their owne power, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted the ſaid <hi>Gelders</hi> Nation, and haue not onely kept them from comming abroad, but alſo haue falne in their owne dominions, and haue forced them to lay downe their Armes.</p>
            <p>But as euery thing in this world is not euerlaſting, ſo this Towne alſo hath ſuffered many ſeuerall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and alterations, and was twice almoſt burnt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14752:7"/>downe. The firſt and greateſt fire was in the yeere 1419, on the 28 of Iune: the ſecond fire in the yeere 1463 the 17 of Iune, at the <hi>Heuſdens</hi> Faire. The firſt fire began in the <hi>Verwer</hi>-ſtreet, neere the ſigne of the Braſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Kettle: by which fire, the Towne-houſe, and all the Papers and Writings, were altogether burnt. The ſecond fire began neere the ſigne of the Falcon in the <hi>Hintemer</hi>-ſtreet, where the top of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church and many Images were alſo burnt.</p>
            <p>The name of the Duke of <hi>Braband,</hi> by whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the towne of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> was built, we haue forborne to ſet downe in this Hiſtory, becauſe of the diuerſity of the Hiſtorians, and haue kept this diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent till the laſt. The common preſumption is, that the Duke <hi>Godfrey</hi> in the Cradell, hath beene the Founder of <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> which is confirmed by theſe words:</p>
            <q>GodrIdVs dVX è sILVa feCIt oppidVM.</q>
            <p>The Duke <hi>Godfrey</hi> hath of a Boſcage built a towne, in the yeere 1184.</p>
            <p>Others preſume that <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt ſonne of <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey</hi> the third hath built this towne.</p>
            <p>The Hiſtorie written before the Chronicle of Saint <hi>Truden,</hi> ſaith, In the County of <hi>Peeland</hi> is a Boſcage, which the Emperours haue giuen vnto the Church of <hi>Vtricht,</hi> whoſe right hath appertained a long time vnto the Counts of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> which ſaid Counts haue giuen the ſame Boſcage vnto their friends, and haue ſold the Village called <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ucht</hi> vnto the Duke <hi>Henry van Looteringen,</hi> who hath built vpon <hi>Oortens-dyck,</hi> a towne which is now <hi>S'herto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genboſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others ſay, that in the time of <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſecond, and <hi>Iohn</hi> the third Dukes of <hi>Braband,</hi> there were
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14752:7"/>firſt made Walles about this place by one <hi>William de Boſco,</hi> Knight, ſonne of <hi>Gerlacus de Route,</hi> who did liue in the yeere 1313, when the <hi>Geerlinger</hi> Bridge in the <hi>Hintemer</hi> ſtreet was builded, and got the name of it. This Knight dying, gaue vnto the Lord of <hi>Erp,</hi> the Cloyſter called <hi>Clariſſen</hi> in the <hi>Hintemer</hi> ſtreet, and made his onely heyre the Lord <hi>Francis,</hi> in September, <hi>Anno</hi> 1335.</p>
            <p>Some ſay alſo, that the place of this Towne here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hath beene a Boſcage or Wood, appertaining vnto the Duke of <hi>Gelderland,</hi> who hath giuen this place vnto <hi>John</hi> the ſecond ſonne of <hi>John</hi> the firſt Duke of <hi>Braband,</hi> for a Gift at his Chriſtening, and that the Towne of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> is ſcituated and built on this place.</p>
            <p>They ſay alſo, that the ſaid Duke <hi>Iohn</hi> hath fold and aſsigned the ſaid Boſcage vnto the ſaid <hi>William de Boſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> from whence he hath gotten his ſurname: And that this <hi>William de Boſco</hi> hath beene the firſt that hath made Walles about the Towne, and admitted euery one that would come and liue there.</p>
            <p>Although it ſeemes that theſe three opinions are contrary one to another, notwithſtanding, they may very well agree together, yea concurre one with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other,</p>
            <p>As concerning the two firſt opinions, euery one can well iudge it: for that <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond liued in the yeeee 1185, when his Father <hi>Godfrey</hi> did raigne. And it is the vſe of all Hiſtorians, that when Kings and Princes raigne during their ſonnes liues, that all that which happened in ſuch a time, is written both of the Fathers and children.</p>
            <p>Concerning the third opinion there will not bee much difference, for that it is to bee vnderſtood of the principall part, namely, from the Priſoner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate to the <hi>Pinappels</hi> and Saint <hi>Anthonies</hi> Gates,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14752:8"/>Againſt this doth not contradict, that it is not men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned there of the beginning of <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> for that it is the biggeſt and faireſt part, hauing in his ringle the great S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, the great Hoſpitall the Holy Ghoſt, or the Spint, the <hi>Gregorians Frater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the Siſter of <hi>Ortens</hi> Cloyſter, the great Begging-Cloyſter, with many other Cloyſters three following the rule of Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> and one of Saint <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus,</hi> one of Saint <hi>Clara,</hi> and many beautifull Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pels, as, Saint <hi>Iacobs</hi> Chappell, which is now a Pariſh Church, one of Saint <hi>Anthonies.</hi> The <hi>Synechdochies</hi> manner of ſpeaking is, where a part is taken for the whole, it is very common vnto the writers.</p>
            <p>Laftly, it is knowne, that in the time of the ſaid Knight, <hi>William de Boſco,</hi> the Towne was augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as by the Letters of the Duke of <hi>Braband,</hi> and of the Magiſtrates of <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> more at large may appeare.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thus farre</hi> Simon Pelgrom <hi>of</hi> S'hertogenboſh, <hi>Prior and Prouinciall of the Order of</hi> Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmines.</p>
            <p>THis Towne of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> did from time to time increaſe ſo much, that at the laſt it was growne to be the head or chiefe Towne in the fourth quarter of <hi>Braband,</hi> vnder whoſe obedience are theſe foure Counties, as <hi>Kempenland, Peeland, Maaeſland,</hi> and the Land of <hi>Ooſterwicke;</hi> in which Counties are ſituated the Townes of <hi>Helmont, Eynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoue, Megen,</hi> and <hi>Graue,</hi> hauing beſides theſe vnder their command 72 Villages, in the which are one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and one Pariſh Churches.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> lyeth vpon the Riuer called the <hi>Dieſe,</hi> 6 Miles from the <hi>Maſe,</hi> 12 miles from <hi>Rauensteine,</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:14752:8"/>9 miles from <hi>Heuſden,</hi> and 36 miles from <hi>Antwerpe.</hi> It is by nature a ſtrong place, becauſe of her ſituation, and low grounds round about, which lieth moſt times vnder water, ſpecially in the Winter, except on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter</hi> ſide, Southward of the Towne, where, for the highneſſe of the Land, the Towne is ſortified with 2. Royall Forts, the one lying neere the Towne, beeing the ſmalleſt is called S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Anthony:</hi> The other lying on the <hi>Vuchters-heyde,</hi> hauing fiue Bulworkes, Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebray Counterſcarps, and a double Ditch, named the Fort <hi>Iſabella.</hi> Eaſtward of the Towne lyeth a Royall Fort called <hi>Pettler-Sconce,</hi> towards which they muſt come by water thorow the <hi>Hekell,</hi> becauſe it ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth as it were in a Myre, hauing on the one ſide a ſmall moore or damp, then followeth high ground, but on the other ſide Iow fields, being ſtill vnder wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding that theſe Lands round about <hi>S'hertohenboſh</hi> lye moſt times vnder water, they are good and firme Lands, ſandie and hard ground, which is for the moſt part of ſummer very dry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in ſome part of it is ſowne ſummer Corne, as Oates and Barley, which are ſometimes ouerflowed by the high waters of the <hi>Maes,</hi> and ſuffer ſometimes dammage, which is hardly recouered, except it be by an extraordinary dry Summer.</p>
            <p>Thorow this Towne runne alſo ſeuerall waters, or ſmall riuers, hauing their beginnings out of two ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſtreames, the one being called the <hi>Aa,</hi> the other the <hi>Dommell,</hi> or <hi>Domale:</hi> which two Riuers in this laſt Siege were ſtopped by the command of his Princely Excellency about the Trenches, who making the water to come round about his Workes, through a new made ditch, about 30 foot wide. The water in and about the Towne was ſtayed with two ſtone beeres on the Bulworkes, next to the boome, as alſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14752:9"/>on the boome it ſelfe, with a Sluce doore, elſe it would haue runne in a great part, yea almoſt round about the Towne, if the ſaid Riuer had not beene ſtopped.</p>
            <p>In the yeere 1577. on the 21 of <hi>September</hi> (in the time of the gouernment of <hi>Don Iohn</hi>) the ſaid Towne being by the command of the generall States, releaſed from the Dutch Souldiers, which lay in the Towne, remained on the States ſide till the yeere 1579. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Garriſon, notwithſtanding, the States vſed great diligence to aſſure this Towne with Garriſon, according to the agreement made at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tricht.</hi> Albeit that at laſt, by reaſon of the differences amongſt the Burgers, (for this cauſe) and of the departure of thoſe that were minded towards the States, is turned on the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſo remained popiſh, wherein came a great number of Eccleſiaſticall perſons.</p>
            <p>On the 19 of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> in the yeere 1585. there was made an enterprize vpon the ſaid Towne, by the Count of <hi>Hohenloo,</hi> they were already in the Towne, but were, by reaſon of the bad carriage of his Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and the good courage of the Burgers; beaten out of the Towne backe againe, with the loſſe of many men, ſlaine, hurt, and taken priſoners, and ſo remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnmoleſted till the yeere 1601. the firſt of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uember, vpon which day, the ſaid Towne, by the command of the high and mighty Lords the States, was beſieged, vnder the Conduct of the Illuſtrious Prince <hi>Mauritius</hi> of <hi>Naſsawe</hi> of famous Memory, and was with great diligence entrenched round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: but becauſe of the great extraordinary froſt, he was not onely hindered of the approaching, the get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Victuals. Munitions, and other neceſſaries, but alſo thoſe that watcht in their Sentinels, were dead frozen: therefore the ſaid Prince broke vp his ſaid Leager, and departed from thence the 27 of the ſame moneth of Nouember.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:14752:9"/>
In the yeere 1603 this ſaid Siege was againe vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken on the 19 of Auguſt: but becauſe the Arch-Duke <hi>Albertas</hi> did lye ready with a great Armie of Souldiers, for to ſeeke his fortune vpon theſe Lands, therefore he followed the ſaid Prince on the 21 of the ſame moneth, leaguering himſelfe on the Eaſt ſide of the Towne, in the which at that time there was but a ſmall Garriſon, and beſides they did refuſe to take in any Garriſon vpon the requeſt of the Arch-Duke ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they themſelues were ſtrong enough to reſiſt their enemies: but there was, by the practice of the ſaid Duke, put into the Towne about 3000 men, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Burgers will, who thereupon did mutiny: wherefore ſome of them were puniſhed. His ſaid Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence ſeeing that the ſaid Towne was thus proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, did with good order breake vp his Leager, and leſt the Towne on the 5 of Nouember, in the ſame yeere, as likewiſe the Arch-duke, departing euery one in their Garriſon. The Gouernour, the Lord <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Shets,</hi> Lord of <hi>Grobbendoncke,</hi> remained in the Towne.</p>
            <p>The High and mighty Lords the States generall, with the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> hauing nothing ſo at heart as the welfare of theſe vnited Prouinces, and the good Inhabitants of the ſame, haue in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this yeere 1629, kept ſeuerall Aſſemblies with the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> for to haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy all things neceſſary for a braue ſiege, hauing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to that end, ſent betimes in the beginning of the yeere, through the Riuer the <hi>Wael,</hi> vp towards <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megen,</hi> and to the Sconce <hi>S'Grauenweert,</hi> ſome Bridges, and ſlat bottom'd ſhips with Ordnance, Munition, and other warlike prouiſions. Whereupon, in the middeſt ef the moneth of Aprill, the Garriſon follo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed, who had their Rendezvous about the ſaid Sconce.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14752:10"/>
The Illuſtrious Prince, the 24 of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning betimes, at ſix of the clocke, with a good reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, departed from the <hi>Hage,</hi> with valiant and braue Followers, taking his way towards <hi>Vtriclat,</hi> ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Arnhem,</hi> and from thence to <hi>S'Grauenweert,</hi> where his Excellency finding his Troopes ready, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted with great diligence for <hi>Mockerheyde,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting there on the 28 of the ſame moneth his Army in Battell-aray, where they that night lay in the Field. The 29 of the ſaid moneth, early in the morning, marching further towards the Towne called <hi>Graus,</hi> ouer the Bridge, right to the <hi>Beſh,</hi> before which Towne that night the Prince ſent ſome number of Horſe, and the next day, being the 30, hee beſet the ſame Towne: then his Excellency came with his whole Army before the Towne, after Dinner, at 3 of the clocke in the afternoone, taking his quarter, with 134 Companies, at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ucht,</hi> lodging in the houſe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Heyms-houſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Excellencie had further ſeparated the other chiefe Quarters as followeth:</p>
            <p>His Highneſſe Count <hi>Ernſt</hi> at <hi>Hintem</hi> with 50 Companies.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>William</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Heuſden,</hi> at <hi>Orten</hi> with 32 Companies.</p>
            <p>The Lord of <hi>Bredrode</hi> about the <hi>Pettler Sconce</hi> with 26 Companies.</p>
            <p>His Highneſſe of <hi>Solms</hi> at <hi>Engelen,</hi> neere <hi>Creueceur,</hi> where the Ships lay with Munition and Victuals.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Pincen</hi> comming in the Leager on the 11 of <hi>May,</hi> he is commanded to take his Quarter at <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teren:</hi> Further, the Quarters were appointed and made vp in a very ſhort ſpace.</p>
            <p>In the matching toward the <hi>Boſh,</hi> the ſaid Prince tooke the houſe called <hi>Heeſwicke,</hi> ſcituated 6 miles from the <hi>Boſh,</hi> in which were 60. men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:14752:10"/>
The Gouernour <hi>Grobbendoncke</hi> being aduertiſed that the Leaguer was comming for the Towne, ſeeing alſo ſome of our Horſemen, notwithſtanding, would not beleeue that it was intended vpon him, but thought that it was intended vpon <hi>Breda;</hi> yea durſt freely ſay, that the Prince would not beginne ſuch a vile deede: but ſhortly after this, ſeeing him make his Quarters, and that our Souldiers came neerer the Towne, and forced his Souldiers to retire in the ſame, began to thinke vpon his owne fault, that the ſaid towne was not ſufficiently prouided of men, Ordnance, and Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder; he could a little while before haue gotten from <hi>Luike</hi> many thouſand pounds of Gunpowder, but he left it for want of money.</p>
            <p>Theſe tydings being come at <hi>Bruſſels</hi> and in <hi>Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,</hi> did make great alterations there: the Arch-Duches did preſently ſend Poſt by Poſt to <hi>Spaine,</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the chiefe men of Warre to be aſſembled, and gaue order for payment: that with all ſpeed the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers ſhould be brought in the Field.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Grobbendoncke</hi> did preſently write for men and powder, and that there ſhould be haſte made for the releeuing of it.</p>
            <p>Certaine renowned chiefe men of Warre of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide, ſaid, (as is told me) with laughing mouth, that <hi>Grobbendoncke</hi> was like the bold men, which ſay that they are not afraid for the Deuill, ieſting at all times with him, yea, would faine ſee him, but being in ſuch a caſe, they are as much afraide as others, wiſhing that they were releaſed from him: ſo it is with him, for that hee oftentimes did ſay, that hee would very faine haue vs to come and ſee him, wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Prince <hi>Fredericke</hi> durſt doe ſo, he would ſhew him what a man hee was, thinking that other chiefe men of Warre were not ſo couragious: But now, ſeeing him before the Gates and Walles of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14752:11"/>Towne, he is as all the reſt, wiſhing that he would goe away.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>May</hi> the Illuſtrious Prince did condiſcend, that many, women Beggins, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant Maids, ſhould depart out of the Towne. The Horſemen which lay within, thought alſo, without permiſsion of the Prince, to depart out of the ſame, but were forced to retire backe againe.</p>
            <p>Betweene the 4 and 5 of the ſame moneth, came into the Towne 800 men, ſecretly along <hi>Vlimen,</hi> neere <hi>Deuteren,</hi> by the <hi>Kee-Sconce,</hi> and ſo got in through S. <hi>Johns</hi> Gate, going in ſome places vp to the midſt of the body in water: for which his Excellence cauſed alſo there to be made a broad way of Bauens, with a Bulwarke from the <hi>Vuchter-heyde</hi> along thorow the Moores, neere the <hi>Vogel-key</hi> of <hi>Grobendoncke,</hi> vntill the Quarter of <hi>Pinſen</hi> being garniſhed with many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>douts made of Wood, and is called the <hi>Hollans</hi> Walls which way of Bauens is made out farther along the Riuer called the <hi>Boſh-ſloot,</hi> to the Village called <hi>Enge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</hi> And ſo with this all the Leager round about is finiſhed within the ſpace of 8 or 10 dayes.</p>
            <p>The 5, Captaine <hi>Drop</hi> was put as Admirall ouen the ſhallops.</p>
            <p>The 8 of this ſaid Moneth there were fetcht ſome halfe Curtowes out of the ſhips at <hi>Crenecour,</hi> and were brought to the Leager, for to bee planted vpon the Batteries.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the Towne began alſo to labour very ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly on their Workes without the <hi>Vuchter</hi>-gate, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king their Batteries higher, but ſhot very little. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this Towne the Lord of <hi>Bredrode</hi> began to make a Sconce ouer againſt the <hi>Pettler,</hi> and all the Workes were by the command of his Excellence, made high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, thicker, and the Ditches wider.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:14752:11"/>
The 12 the <hi>Dommell</hi> was beſpoken to be ſtopt, or to make a Damme ouer it.</p>
            <p>At night, thoſe of the Towne came out with two ſhallops vpon the Quarter of Count <hi>Ernſt,</hi> thinking there to take ſome Priſoners, but they hauing misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, did ſpeedily retire backe againe, whereupon they of the Towne did ſhoot with Ordnance and Muskets, but did ſmall hurt.</p>
            <p>This Leager is preſumed to bee betweene 60 and 70 thouſand men ſtrong, whereof were 70 Cornets of Horſe.</p>
            <p>The 14, about forty flat-bottome Turfe-ſhippes were fetcht from <hi>S'Grauenmoer,</hi> neere <hi>Breda,</hi> and were brought in the Leager, for to make of the ſame Ship-bridges. The 15, thoſe did ſalley vpon the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Lord of <hi>Brederode,</hi> but were cauſed with forces to retire backe againe. The 16 are thoſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in come out againe with ſome ſhallops, vpon the quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Count <hi>Eruſt,</hi> but were faine to retire without doing any thing.</p>
            <p>The 20 we began to make a Trench betweene <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelen</hi> and <hi>Creueceur,</hi> for the ſecurity of the Horſes: and all other Trenches with double bankets or feet-ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: the foot of the Trench was about 16 foot thick, and the vpper part 6 foot. Neere the place called <hi>Vliemer brugge</hi> ouer againſt the high-way, is made a Fort which can hardly be taken, to reſiſt thoſe of <hi>Breda</hi> that would come out. On the 23 there came a Meſſenger with Letters, which was followed by ours, ſo that he was drowned; whoſe ſaid Letters were deliuered vnto the Prince. The 27, 28, 29, &amp; 30 of the ſame moneth, we ſhot on both ſides very fiercely though there was but ſmall hurt done.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>June,</hi> thoſe of the great Fort <hi>Iſabella</hi> did make a ſalley vpon the <hi>French</hi> Battery, but were at laſt forced to retire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:14752:12"/>
The night following, thoſe of the Towne did make three ſeuerall fires vpon the ſteeple of the Church, weighing the fire three times vp and downe. The <hi>French</hi> did fall vpon the Enemies, and cauſed them to retire, and got many Shouels, Spades, Swords, and other things.</p>
            <p>The 3 and 4 thoſe of the Towne made againe a fire vpon the ſteeple of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Johns</hi> Church: And the 5, 6, 7, and 8 of this Moneth, there was little done on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The 9, ours of the great Battery did ſhoote vpon the Towne and the little Sconce aboue 140 ſhot. The ſame day thoſe of the Towne came out with two ſhallops vpon the Quarter of <hi>Pinſen,</hi> thinking there to take ſome Horſes, and men which were at worke, but were hindred.</p>
            <p>The 11 there arriued in the Quarter of Count <hi>Ernſt</hi> yet 18 or 19 Companies of new <hi>Scotchmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 12 and 13 little hapned.</p>
            <p>The 14 His Excellencie, with the Lords the States, went vpon the Battery, and cauſed a Morter to be ſet on fire, which ſtood vpon the ſame Battery, which the firſt time did not worke very well: but the ſecond time much more, ſo that for the duſt we could ſcarce ſee the ſaid Sconce: the little Sconce was likewiſe battered: and betweene the 13 and 14, there were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine made 3 fires vpon the ſteeple.</p>
            <p>The 15 there were throwne into the Sconces ſixe Granads, whereof the ſecond did worke very well, ſo that the Hurts did fly in the ayre. The ſame day, the water of the <hi>Dommell</hi> was let go in the outmoſt ditch round about the Princes quarter.</p>
            <p>The 16 at night, thoſe within did make a ſalley, (comming through the <hi>Hintemer</hi> Gate, vpon the Workes of Count <hi>Ernst,</hi> cauſing the Watch to retire to the Battery: notwithſtanding, they were forced
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:14752:12"/>to retyre. The 18 there were throwne into the little Sconce two or three Granads.</p>
            <p>The ſame day at night, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were buſie to fill the ditch of the little Sconce. The <hi>French</hi> were at that time alſo very buſie, making that night three bints of their Gallery neere the great Sconce. The next night thoſe of the Towne did very fiercely throw with hand-Granads and firing with pitch hoopes.</p>
            <p>The 20, ours did labour in open day vpon the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries, and did throw 8 Granats into the little Sconce, which cauſed all that they came neere to flye in the Ayre, the men did withdrawe themſelues into the Counterſcarps, to ſaue their liues. Thoſe of the towne did make three ſeuerall fires vpon the ſteeple.</p>
            <p>The 21 there were Granads throwne againe into the little Sconce which was thereupon very much beaten with Ordnance.</p>
            <p>The 22 at night, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were very buſie vpon their Gallery, which was for the third time ſet on fire by thoſe of the Sconce: notwithſtanding the ſaid <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> were very couragious, beating their enemies out of their Counterſcarpes in the ditch, where many of them were drowned.</p>
            <p>The 23 the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were againe very forward with their Gallery: likewiſe the French, who did ſet on fire a Mine neere the great Sconce.</p>
            <p>At which time Count <hi>Henry van den Bergh</hi> did muſter his men, and was found to bee about 25000 men ſtrong, aſwell of foot as Horſe.</p>
            <p>The 24 and 25 hapned very little.</p>
            <p>The 26. there was vpon three ſeuerall places in the Leaguer a fire, namely in the Horſemens Quarter, in the Quarter of <hi>Brederode,</hi> and in the Quarter of His princely Excellency, amongſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> where there was done the moſt dammage.</p>
            <p>Count <hi>Henry van den Bergh</hi> being a marching vp,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14752:13"/>did lodge himſelfe in <hi>Langheſtraet,</hi> at <hi>Sprang, Wael<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke, Druynen,</hi> and <hi>Loon-opt-land.</hi> His Maieſty of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia</hi> came this night in the Leager, and went with His Excellency to ſee all his Workes. The 27 came the Horſemen of Count <hi>Henry van den bergh</hi> at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſhewing himſelfe on ſeuerall parts of the Leager, from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lymen</hi> to <hi>Cromvoort.</hi> At night there was an Allarum in the Towne.</p>
            <p>The 28 there was in the Quarter of <hi>Count Ernſt</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine a fire in two ſeuerall places. At night, Count <hi>henry van den bergh</hi> ſhewed himſelfe neere the <hi>Three Siſters,</hi> neere the <hi>Hollands Wall:</hi> amongſt which ours ſhot 10 or 12 Cannon ſhot, whereupon they did pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently retire. Our Souldiers were in battell-array all this night. The 29 there came ſome Souldiers in the Leager, which were runne away from the Enemies, complaining of hunger and great dearth. The 30 the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> did hide themſelues in the Wood behinde the <hi>Ynffer-Sconce,</hi> who got ſome Waggons with Bauens of our Leaguer, and about 40 priſoners: They tooke alſo the Houſes <hi>Burtell</hi> and <hi>Heſop,</hi> the Souldiers which were in the ſame, came with their full Armes &amp; bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage into the Leager: beſides, they came betimes in the morning with 2 ſhallops from <hi>Vlymen,</hi> to the <hi>three Siſters</hi> and <hi>Hollands Wall,</hi> to ſound the depth of the water; whereupon the whole Leager came in battell aray. Some that were run away from the Enemies, declared, that in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Army, a pound of Cheeſe was worth 12 Stiuers, and a Kan of Beere 6 Stiuers, and all other things accordingly.</p>
            <p>The 2 of <hi>Iuly, Monſieur Fama</hi> was hurt with a ſhot thorow the body, and dyed immediately. The 4 at night, the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> came againe vpon the Leaguer, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which we played very fiercely with our Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance from the outermoſt Batteries: wherupon they were forced to retire, leauing behind them ſome dead
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14752:13"/>men and hurt. At that ſame time they thought alſo to breake thorow along the Wall of the <hi>Dommell,</hi> but were alſo hindred of it. Thoſe that wee tooke priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, complained of great hunger, miſery, and bad payment. This was the tenth time that they tryed their fortune againſt the Leager, which made vs to ſtand euery night in Battell-ray. This night thoſe within the Towne did make againe three ſeuerall fires vpon the ſteeple. Alſo wee tooke priſoners ſome of the Boores which did meaſure the depth of the water, and thought to bring them through it, of which two were hanged in the Quarter of his Excellencie: The one was a Borrow-maſter of <hi>Beckhonen,</hi> and the other a Boore of <hi>Vucht:</hi> they confeſſed to haue receiued each 20 Gilders, and that they ſhould haue had with them 600 men, which ſhould haue brought into the towne each of them 10 pounds of Gunpowder. The 6 the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>French</hi> haue brought ouer their Galleries before both the Sconces. Betweene the 7 and eighth thoſe of the Great Sconce made a ſalley, but were bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten backe againe, leauing behind them about 40 men aſwell dead as hurt. The <hi>Spaniſh</hi> marched from <hi>Cran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voort,</hi> and the places there-about, towards <hi>Boxell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 9 the <hi>French</hi> haue taken the Hornenworke of the great Sconce: there was begun an inner Trench from the Quarter of <hi>Pinſen</hi> to the <hi>Three Siſters:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe from the Quarter of His Excellencie to the Sconce of <hi>Brederode:</hi> and from thence neere the Cloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at <hi>Eyken-donck</hi> vnto the Quarter of his Highneſſe Count <hi>Ernſt,</hi> and are well prouided with Redouts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thoſe within. The 12 the Coronelſhip of Monſ. <hi>Fama</hi> late, is giuen vnto Count <hi>Maurits</hi> of <hi>Naſſawe.</hi> The 14 the 2 water-mils neere the <hi>Dieſe,</hi> together with 21 other water-mils to bee vſed with Horſes, were to be mended, therewith to make dry the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land. The 16 Count <hi>Henry vanden bergh</hi> marched vp
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14752:14"/>with his whole Army from <hi>Boxtel,</hi> making a Bridge neere <hi>Moock</hi> ouer the <hi>Maes,</hi> hee himſelfe remaining neere <hi>Moocke.</hi> The 17 there was a Boore taken priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, who thought to bring a Letter into the towne, by which Count <hi>Henry van den bergh</hi> commended vnto the Gouernour <hi>Grobbendoncke</hi> to keepe good Watch, ſaying that hee would take no aduantage vpon the Leager for to relieue the towne. Of this tenor:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>MY Lord Seeing that it is impoſsible to beate away the Enemies out of their Workes, with the Men which I haue ready, becauſe he lyeth very faſt, more then ordinary fortified: I finde it good to breake vp my Leager, and to tranſport my ſelfe by the Jmperialiſts, who are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in Armes, and a great many of them are departed for <hi>Weſell,</hi> aſwell of Horſe as Foot, hoping to doe ſuch a notable deede, that the Enemies ſhall bee forced to fight with vs; and that in that cauſe God will make vs to haue the Victory, and that thereby the Towne ſhall bee relieued, if you can keepe the ſame yet for a time: which I would hereby make knowne vnto you. I pray you, when you haue receiued this, that you then in the night make a great fire vpon the ſteeple of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, mouing the ſame ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times: and to make the next day a great ſmoke on the ſaid ſteeple, by which J ſhall know that this Letter is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered vnto you: and when this Meſsenger ſhall depart againe with anſwer, you ſhall then the night following doe the ſame token with fire, and then the day following againe with ſmoke along time. Meane while J reſt,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your louing &amp; faithfull friend, <hi>Henry van den Bergh.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>In the Leager at</hi> Box<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, <date>Iuly <hi>16. 1629.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <postscript>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Superſcription is,</hi> To my Lord, My Lord the Baron of <hi>Grobbendoncke,</hi>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:14752:14"/>Knight of the Order of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iacob</hi> Collonell of a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Wallons, Gouernour of <hi>Shertogenboſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </postscript>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>But this Letter being come into the hands of His Excellency, he did ſend it vnto the Lords the States of the vnited Prouinces, with his aduice what order and what meanes there ſhould be imployed to hinder the deſigne of the Enemies, and he himſelfe gaue or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to follow the Enemy with as many men as hee could ſpare out of his Leager, to continue and aduance this Siege.</p>
            <p>The 18 the Lord <hi>Dieden,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Emmericke,</hi> hath taken in the morning at three of the clocke, the great Sconce, finding in the ſame 10 Hogsheads of Wine, 24 Tunnes of Beere, and ſome bread and Porke. The next following, the Colonell <hi>Harwits</hi> got alſo the little Sconce, finding in the ſame much Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour and Houſhold-ſtuffe.</p>
            <p>The 24 the Prince heard that Count <hi>Henry van den bergh</hi> was fallen into the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elewe,</hi> whereupon there were ſent thither ſome of the chiefe men of War, with a great number of Souldiers of Foot and Horſe, for to ſecure the <hi>Betuwe</hi> and other places from his Deſigne. the 25 and 28 thoſe within haue with two ſhallops brought into the Towne ſome priſoners. The 28 ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued in the Leager the yong Prince of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> who will ſtay there a while.</p>
            <p>The 3 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Ruſh bridge was brought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. The 4 we tooke in the <hi>Tanaille</hi> before the <hi>Vuch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> gate, notwithſtanding thoſe within did beate vs out againe. The 7 at night the ſaid <hi>Tanaille</hi> was taken, and preſently there was made a Battery of the ſame.</p>
            <p>The 10 at night there came two Boores out of the towne, each with a couple of Pigeons, and 3 Letters, which Letters were brought to the Prince: the tenor of them was, that they were to be relieued within 3. weekes: the 13, 14, &amp; 15 was on both ſides very
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14752:15"/>fiercely plaid with Ordnance, and ſome Granads were throwne into the Towne, which cauſed great outcries in the ſame. Thoſe within came out vpon the Trench northward of <hi>Brederodens</hi> Quarter, neere the water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milles, thinking to cut thorow the ſame, which being almoſt done, they were beaten backe againe Between the 17 and 18, thoſe which came out with ſome ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops, vpon the Battery betweene <hi>Pinſens</hi> Quarter and the great Sconce, ſpoiled the victualers; but found no Ordnance, becauſe it is euery night brought vnder the great Sconce, and ſo returned backe into the Towne. The 19 there was a Mine ſprung in the Hornenworke neere the <hi>Hintemer</hi> end, which killed many men; notwithſtanding thoſe within defended themſelues three ſeuerall times, and kept the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
            <p>After that his Highneſſe Count <hi>Ernſt</hi> had well beſet the <hi>Betuwe,</hi> and other places neere the <hi>Iſſel</hi> ſtreame, for to hinder the comming of the Enemies, (which were already falne in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>elewe</hi>) with braue and chiefe men, well conſidering of all things: thereupon the Prince alſo did ſend thither men of Horſe and foot as many as his Excellency could well ſpare, ſhewing himſelfe day and night (fearing not any danger) euery where in the vttermoſt of the Workes and batteries; then there came on the 20 this joyfull Letter, from the Worthy, Worſhipfull man of Warre, <hi>Otto van Gent</hi> and <hi>Oyen,</hi> Lord of <hi>Dieden,</hi> &amp;c. vnto the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince of <hi>Orenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MY Lord, The bearer hereof, my Couſin</hi> Mederode, <hi>commeth to bring your Excellency report of the good ſucceſſe of the taking of the Towne of</hi> Weſell. <hi>The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my did leaue at that ſame time</hi> 2 <hi>Forts or Sconces, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtaying that wee ſhould ſhoot vpon them. They haue bored to the ground their ſhips of Warre: and hauing ſome
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14752:15"/>Bridges vpon the</hi> Rhyne, <hi>I haue burnt part of them, which were not fit. Here is a great number of Ordnance, and</hi> 13 <hi>or</hi> 14 <hi>Boats ſet vpon Waggons. I haue, for the better aſſurance of the Towne ſent vnto the Gouernors of</hi> Rhees <hi>and</hi> Emericke, <hi>that they would ſend me ſome Companies of Foot. And if your Excellence thinketh fit. I wiſh to haue a great many more men, wherewith, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>In</hi> Weſell, <hi>in haste,</hi> 
                        <date>Auguſt 19. 2629.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your Excellencies humble and obedient, <hi>Otto van Gent</hi> and <hi>Oyen.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Whereupon there was a generall Thankeſgiuing through all the Leager for this Victory; and we haue made Bonfires after the Leager manner, as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</p>
            <p>His Excellency commanded that none ſhould begin before the Signall of the <hi>Jacht</hi> before <hi>Creueceur</hi> was done. The Princeſſe was her ſelfe vpon the Walles of <hi>Creueceur,</hi> and the <hi>Yacht</hi> play'd his Canon; then thoſe of the Fort <hi>Creueceur</hi> did play with 18 Peeces, and played thoſe of the Redouts along the <hi>Boſh-ſloot,</hi> then the Lord <hi>Pinſen,</hi> then the great and little Sconces, and then the Ordnance about the Quarter of the Prince of <hi>Orenge;</hi> then after thoſe the Quarter of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derode</hi> from his Fort againſt the <hi>Pettler,</hi> then his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Count <hi>Ernſt</hi> with his whole and halfe Curtows, as alſo at <hi>Orten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Ordnance had thus played at all places, then beganne likewiſe all the Muskettiers of the whole Leaguer. Thoſe of the Quarter of his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Excellency beganne firſt, and then they followed Eaſtward the one after the other, round about the Leager, as a running Fire. The Pike-men, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of the Horſemen did carry burthens of Straw
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14752:16"/>vpon their Pikes and ſtaues going ſo through all parts of the Leager, that it made a great light. When the ſecond charge of the Canon began, was caſt into the Towne a Morter: the ſhips (lying by hundreds toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther along the <hi>Dieſe</hi>) did make Bonefires with pitch-Barrels and did hang out Lanthorns vpon their Maſts. In ſumme, it was like as if the whole Leager had bin on fire. The 26 at night went forth 2 companies of Horſemen, and 200 Fire. lockes, which met by the way a Conuoy that went for <hi>Breda,</hi> of which ours killed ſome and brought priſoners with them 40 men and about 80 Horſes well furniſhed: Alſo a Ritmaſter and a Lieutenant, with a Cornet: for the Waggons was giuen ſecurity. The 30 a Boere or a carrier of let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters was hanged here in the Leager, after he had beene impriſoned about 10 weekes. Betweene the 30 and 31, the Gallery on the Weſt ſide of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter-gate</hi> was brought ouer; and the ninth binte of the other Gallery on the South ſide of the ſaid Bulwarke (which the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>4 was appointed to be made) was brought ouer.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>September,</hi> ours that were in the Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke, began to breake from the ſaid Bulwarke in the Walles of the Town, which was about 12 foot thicke, and there to make a Mine. On this day <hi>Monſieur Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenbroeck</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Bouillon,</hi> with ten Cornets of Horſe, three Peeces of Ordnance, and ſome hundred Fire-lockes, are marched toward the little towne cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Endhouen,</hi> and got the ſame, with the Caſtle, which lyes there, on the ſecond of the ſame moneth, with agreement, or compoſition. About 200 men, which did withdrawe themſelues from thence in a Moore neere that place, part of them were defeated by the Duke <hi>de Bouillon,</hi> and about 160 were brought priſoners into the Leager. Betweene the 9 and 10 in the morning, the Illuſtrious Prince did ride towards the Mine which he did cauſe to ſpring, and it did work
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14752:16"/>well, ſpringing to the <hi>Vuchter-gaete.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> had the Watch there, who fell vpon the Enemy with a great courage, and did ſo beate them out of the ſame, that thee were forced to retire and leaue the Halfe-Moone; they defended themſelues at the firſt well, but ours fell on with a falſe Alarme, likewiſe fell the Enemies with all their forces vpon vs, ours did retire ſomewhat backe, ſo that the Enemies were deceiued, thinking that they had the Victory; whereupon our ſecond Mine ſprung, ſo that armes and leggs flew in the Ayre, whereupon ours fell on againe, and did beat them by force out of the halfe-moone, (as aforeſaid) ſo that we tooke in all their workes on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter</hi>-gate: in which halfemoone we began to worke at 3 of the Clocke, becauſe thoſe of the Towne ſhould not ſhoot in it, we beganne alſo preſently to mine in the ſtone Bulwarke, where on the 11 our Mine ſprung, wherevpon, by the command of his Excellency, ſome of ours did fall, onely to ſee what countenance the Enemies held, which came preſently backe againe, and our Souldiers preſently lodged in the breach of the Mine. Thereupon came a Drummer from the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, hee pretended to aske leaue to dig out two Captaines, which they ſaid were on led in our Mine: the Prince (who was preſent in the Workes) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to be looked for them, which was alſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: vnto thoſe that looked for them, was giuen a <hi>Couinex-daller</hi> by the <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> but it was not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that they did it, becauſe the Drummer came pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently againe, requiring to ſpeake with ſome of our Officers, to report vnto the Prince to treat of a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition; whereupon there came preſently 4 perſons of quality out of the Town, to the Illuſtrious Prince, (who ſate in the Gallery vpon a little bench, being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſome chiefe men, though few in number) ſpeaking there with the ſaid prince, requiring
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14752:17"/>foure dayes, meane while they would ſend vnto the Infanta, and in caſe of default of releeuing in that time, would treat of the rendition of the town which was denyed vnto them; notwithſtanding, they fell to a treaty of a parly, and they haue on both ſides ſent Hoſtages: meane time many Burgers and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call perſons ſhewed themſelues vpon the Walles.</p>
            <p>On the 13 of the ſame moneth, thoſe of the <hi>Boſh</hi> did dine with the Illuſtrious Prince, and after dinner did returne with the Princes Coaches backe againe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Towne, and ours came againe out of the ſame towne; thoſe of the Towne did leaue their Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion with vs, the which, together with the reſolution of the Prince, the high and mighty Lords the States did carry with them into the Towne.</p>
            <p>On Friday the 14, after dinner, about 4 of the clocke, the Compoſition of the rendition of the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and renowned Towne of <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly concluded in the Leager, in the Houſe where the Illuſtrious Prince was lodged, and was by both par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſubſcribed, to the great ioy of ours, aſwell among the chiefe, as common Inhabitants. The Committies are ioyfully departed one from another; and thoſe of the Towne (after they had ſubſcribed the Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) departed with the Princes Coach to the Towne; which were theſe, to wit, <hi>Fr. Michael Epiſcopus Buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus: Fr. Johannes Moores, Abbas Bernenſus: Johan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Hermans, Deccanus Buſcobus: R. van Voorn: T. vanden Velde: R. van Ireneuen: B. Loef vanden Sloot: Henrick Somerts: Peter Huberts, Hercalt Heuel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Meane while there came in the Leager many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand of Burgers from ſeuerall Townes and places, to ſee the braue Siege, the Illuſtrious and Couragious Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and the departure of the Enemies out of <hi>S'hertogenboſh;</hi> of which many were forced to lye all night in the Field.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:14752:17"/>
The 17 the Prince cauſed the men of Warre to bee armed, and there were made 2 Tents neere the towne, wherein were the Illuſtrious Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> being accompanied with his Princeſſe, his Maieſty of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia,</hi> and his Queene, the Prince of <hi>Denmarke,</hi> beſides 40, aſwell Dukes, Counts, as Barons, where thoſe of the Towne did march by them: Firſt there came a Company of Horſe of ours, where thoſe of the towne did paſſe neere: then followed the Waggons and Carres, with ſicke perſons, baggage, Ieſuites, Nunnes, and Friers of all ſorts: betwixt theſe was <hi>Grobben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doncks</hi> wife in a Coach (who was but three weeks out of Childbed) with whom the Prince had a long Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. At laſt at night followed the Gouernour ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon a Horſe, betweene 2 Coronels of ths States: the Footmen were 22 Companies, being about 2000 men ſtrong, together with the ſicke and hurt perſons, whereof there were not aboue 1200 in health: there followed alſo three Companies of Horſe, braue and well armed.</p>
            <p>Of our ſide marched againe into the Towne the Guard of the Illuſtrious Prince, the Company of my Lord <hi>Beuerweert,</hi> and alſo the Company of my Lord <hi>Wits,</hi> beſides ſome other Companies. Alſo in the <hi>Pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler</hi> Sonce many Souldiers. On the 18 there was put an Orenge Ancient on the ſteeple of <hi>S. Iohns</hi> Church: there came many thouſand Burgers from without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Towne: the Burgers within were reaſonably well contented, ſaying that they had not had want of victuals during this Siege, but onely of Butter and Cheeſe, which was very deare.</p>
            <p>On the ſame day came his Princely Excellencie himſelfe into the Towne, but returned preſently againe to the Leager: Many of the high and mighty Lords the States generall, and Deputies of the ſame, are come into the Towne with Coaches,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14752:18"/>and were welcommed of the Magiſtrates, and are lodged at the ſigne of the Sunne.</p>
            <p>On Wedneſday the 19 of this moneth, the Goſpell of God was preached in 3 Churches, and his Princely Excellency, his Maieſty of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> together with the Prince of <hi>Denmarke</hi> being preſent in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, where were baptized three children, to which the ſaid Potentates were Godfathers: namely his Maieſtie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> of the firſt child, called <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melia;</hi> his Princely Excellency of the ſecond child, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Iohannes;</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> of the third child called <hi>Mauritius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord God ſaue and bleſſe from henceforth his Princely Excellency, who hath carried himſelfe in this ſiege as a valiant and braue Souldier, fearing no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, but preſenting himſelfe alwaies perſonally, to the encouragement of his Souldiers, and terrour of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies. There was neuer ſeene in any ſiege in this Countrey, ſo many Dukes, Barons, Gentiles, and Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntiers, which did come out of ſeuerall Kingdomes and places, but onely before this Towne of which no body can ſpeake enough, being all done in a ſhort time. And that the Enemies muſt giue him the honour, that when he came there with his great and ſtrong Armie, he could attempt nothing vpon him, but ſent a Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Towne, and ſo went away.</p>
            <p>For this great Victorie, which the Lord God hath (this yeere) giuen vnto theſe Lands, there is by the high and mighty Lords the States generall ordained and commanded to keepe a Faſt, and day of Prayer, whereupon they gaue out this Letter.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Welbeloued, &amp;c.</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHereas it hath pleaſed the Almighty Lord God to ſhew vs his exceeding great mercy and compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ouer theſe Lands, that he not only hath ſtayed the great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14752:18"/>forces of the Enemies, the which according to all appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, were like to breake thorow in the midſt of the heart of our Land, with deſtruction of goods and liues of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, together with the reformed Religion, as alſo of the liberties, lawes and priuiledges; but that he aboue all this hath greatly bleſsed theſe Lands, with the taking of the Towns of <hi>Weſell</hi> and <hi>S'hertogenboſh,</hi> to the increaſe of his holy Word, and comfort of many, which haue beene many yeeres vnder the tyranny of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the high and mighty Lords the States, haue found very neceſſary to bid and command a generall faſting day, in all the vnited Prouinces, Countries, Shires, and their aſſociate Townes and places, to be on Wedneſday next with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>14</hi> daies, which ſhall be the <hi>10</hi> of October, <hi>ſtilo nouo,</hi> for to giue hearty thankes, praiſe and glory vnto the Lord for all theſe vndeſerued bleſsings, and vnceſſantly to pray, that he will giue vnto the Inhabitants of <hi>S'hertogenboſh</hi> the true knowledge of his holy Goſpell, and to ſend to that and true and faithfull Teachers. Alſo that the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God will be with the Army of this State, as a Lord of all things, for to beate away the Enemies out of our Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and to continue his bleſſings ouer vs: Alſo that hee will defend from all euill and dangers his Excellency the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> and to multiply his daies wtih wiſdome bleſsings and felicity, and to conſerue his perſon, and all his Army in health, to the glory of his holy Name, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of his holy Word. Therefore we require, &amp;c.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>In the <hi>Hage,</hi> 
                        <date>Septemb. <hi>24. 1629.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>In the Towne are choſen new Magiſtrates, and the old are releaſed from their Oathes done to the King of <hi>Spaine.</hi> And Sir <hi>Philips de Thienen,</hi> Coronell ouer the Regiment of his Highneſſe <hi>van Brederode,</hi> is put as Commander ouer the Garriſon. The Burgers are alſo releafed from their Oath vnto the King of <hi>Spaint,</hi> and tooke their Oathes vnto theſe Lands.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="journal">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:14752:19"/>
            <head>A <hi>Iournall</hi> or Day-regiſter of that which is happened within the Towne of <hi>S'hertogen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſh</hi> during the laſt ſiege. Written by one of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> ſide.</head>
            <p>ON the laſt of <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1629, the Enemies came vnto the Sconce <hi>Creueceur,</hi> 150 ſhips ſtrong. The firſt of May they came to <hi>Orten,</hi> and did preſently intrench themſelues from <hi>Orten</hi> to <hi>Hintem,</hi> from <hi>Hintem</hi> to <hi>Dungen,</hi> and to <hi>Gaſtell,</hi> from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ucht</hi> to <hi>Vlymen,</hi> vnto the <hi>Boſh-ſloot,</hi> where they brought about 50 ſhips with Bauens, and further at <hi>Engelen,</hi> where they laboured very earneſtly.</p>
            <p>The 5 there came from <hi>Breda,</hi> along <hi>Flymen,</hi> into the Towne, betweene 8 and 9 hundred men, which went vp to the middle in water.</p>
            <p>The 6 we ſhot with a peece of Ordnance from the great Sconce amongſt 15 Horſemen, of which ſome were flaine.</p>
            <p>The 10 the Captaine <hi>Dirck Buſschieter</hi> with 12 men, did pierce thorow the <hi>Coe</hi>-wall, which the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies (being ſtrong 59 men) thought to hinder our comming thither, but were forced to retire with the loſſe of two men.</p>
            <p>In 14 dayes there is from without happened but very little: for they did nothing elſe but intrench themſelues. At this time the Butter began already to be worth 10 or 12 Stiuers, and yet hardly could any be gotten. Whereupon the Gouernour and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates did command, that all Honey-ſellers, &amp; ſpice-bread-makers ſhould no more vſe or boile any Honey,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14752:19"/>vpon penalty of 100 Dollers to be paid by them that ſhall bee ſound in fault, becauſe they would eate the Honey vpon their bread. The Souldiers could hardly get any victuals, for that they were ſo deare, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was commanded that the Porke ſhould be ſold for 6 ſtiuers a pound, a pound of Butter for 6 ſtiuers, and a pound of Cheeſe for 4 ſtiuers.</p>
            <p>Vntill the 20 the Prince <hi>Fredericke Henricke,</hi> had not ſhot with Ordnance vpon the towne, but becauſe many houſes were to be broken downe, &amp; many trees for to be vſed for his fortification.</p>
            <p>The 22 the Prince cauſed to ſhoot vpon the <hi>Orten</hi>-gate nine ſhots of Canon. We ſaw alſo a battery made by the Enemies at <hi>Hintem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tho ſame day there went out two Meſſengers of ours, which returned for <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> but could not get through, for that the towne was already beſet.</p>
            <p>The ſame day all the houſes were viſited, and all the Corne that was in the towne was ſet downe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the number of all the dwellers.</p>
            <p>The 23 in the morning we ſaw in the ayre ouer the Towne about <hi>Orten,</hi> two Raine-bowes, with the backe one againſt the other, with two Sunnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſaid Raine-bowes, the one aboue the other, what the interpretation is, God knowes.</p>
            <p>The 24 our Souldiers brought in 14 Horſes of the Enemies, which altogether were ſold for 28 Gilders, yet more 3 horſes of the Enemies for 4 ſtiuers and 8 pence, yet another for 3 ſtiuers: a little Carre of Hay did coſt 60 Gilders. The Enemies did ſhoot againe vpon the Towne: and two meſſengers arriued heere thorow the Leager; their report was kept ſecret from the Burgers: we bought a horſe for a ſtiuer; and Mr. <hi>Pauwels</hi> gaue a ſtiuer for the 4 ſhooes. There was a Horſe ſold for a pipe of Tobacco, for which they could haue had 12 pound Flemmiſh two moneths before.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14752:20"/>
The 26 a Herring coſt halfe a ſtiuer, an Egge one ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, a pound of Beefe 5 ſtiuers, Mutton 8 ſtiuers.</p>
            <p>The 27 was publiſhed, that no body ſhould cut downe any wood which was in their Gardens, vpon penalty of 100 Ducats, becauſe the ſame muſt be vſed on the Workes in the Walkes. The ſame day the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies did ſhoot thorow the holy-Croſſe-gate, into the houſe of <hi>Mary Grietmakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 28 we fell vpon the enemies Quarters at <hi>Vucht</hi> and 5 men were ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The 29 we fell out by the <hi>Vuchtergate,</hi> on the <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> and at night at 11 of the clocke wee tooke from the enemies a Corps <hi>de Guarde,</hi> wherein they kept watch. The ſame day wee skirmiſhed a long time with the Enemies.</p>
            <p>The 30 we made an vndermine through the walls of the Towne, ſafely to march towards the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate vpon the Watch; This day the Enemies ſhot very much; and a ſhot came thorow the ſteeple of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, and alſo through the ſteeple neere the <hi>Boome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 31 the Enemies did ſhoot aboue 110 ſhot with halfe Curtowes, by which ſome of the Burgers hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and the Biſhops houſe was damnified, though in this moneth there were none ſlaine by the ſhooting of Cannons, but onely Captaine <hi>Ratelo,</hi> and a Gunner was hurt. The Mils haue alſo till now ground.</p>
            <p>The 1 of <hi>June,</hi> the Captaine <hi>Dommell bergen</hi> gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his Companie for the firſt time. This day &amp; night the Enemies did ſhoot very fiercely vpon the batte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and were approached to the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate more then halfe a Musket ſhot, where there were many Souldiers on both ſides hurt and ſlaine.</p>
            <p>The ſecond on <hi>Whitſon</hi> Eue, wee ſhot very fiercely vpon the Enemies, ſpecially from the <hi>Hintemer-gate,</hi> and the out-works, ſo that euery Muskettier did ſhoot
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14752:20"/>30, 40, or 50 ſhots, whoſe breſts were ſo blew that they could not continue any longer. The Enemies did ſhoot downe with their Ordnance many rare out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes of S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church. Here arriued a meſſenger from <hi>Bruſsels,</hi> whereupon there was at night a fire made upon the ſteeple of the ſaid Church, for a token that the ſaid Meſſenger was ſafely arriued.</p>
            <p>The 3. vpon <hi>Whitſonday,</hi> we bought Beefe yet for 7 and 8 ſtiuers a pound, Murton for 8, 9, &amp; 10 ſtiuers.</p>
            <p>The 4 we fell out of the Towne vpon the Enemies Trenches towards <hi>Vucht,</hi> and defeated many of them. And on the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate, an ancient Souldier had his head ſhot off.</p>
            <p>The 5, on both ſides, aſwell out as vpon the great Sconce was very fiercely ſhot, wherein the <hi>Dutch</hi> which were come out of <hi>Breda,</hi> did defend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues very manfully: wherefore they did mock thoſe of the <hi>Boſh,</hi> ſaying, that they were fit to fetch Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants and Boores, where they doe not feare to bee beaten. The ſame day <hi>Peter Cabuſins,</hi> Conſtable, broght from the little Sconce into the Towne 2 halfe Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>towes. Before the <hi>Vuchter</hi>-gate a man had his legges ſhot off: and a Boy, which came from the Sconce to the Towne, to fetch there a bottle of Wine, was ſlaine in the <hi>Vuchter</hi> gate. At the ſame day, the ſiluer S. <hi>John</hi> on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter</hi> gate his backe was ſhot in pieces.</p>
            <p>The 6, a woman dwelling at the figne of the <hi>Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow,</hi> being in her chamber, both her legs were ſhot off.</p>
            <p>The 7 the Enemies came ſo neere vnder the little Sconce, that they in the Workes did drinke one to another with a Kanne of Beere, and Tobacco, which they did giue one to another with their pikes, and fell prefently to ſhoot againe. The Beggins that were in the Cloiſters, did make Cuſhions for the Souldiers; and the prieſts made hearts to hang about their necks.</p>
            <p>The 8 and 9 they ſhot very fiercely one againſt the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14752:21"/>other. On the 10 the Enemies ſhot thorow S. <hi>Johns</hi> Church, and did hurt a man which was confeſsing his ſinnes: the ſame day a mans head was ſhot off, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Souldiers eare; there were ſhot to this day 1000 ſhot.</p>
            <p>The 11 the Enemies came neere vnto the Sconce before the <hi>Vuchter-gate,</hi> and tooke in the Hornen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke, with maine force.</p>
            <p>The 12 was ſhot on both ſides very fiercely on the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate.</p>
            <p>The 13 and 14 we did ſtill continue our ſhooting, and tooke in ſome Workes from the Enemies, and brought into the Towne 2 Rondaſſes. At night the Enemies did ſet the Captaines houſe on fire with their Granads, in the little Sconce, where alſo flew vp 4 Barrels of Gunpowder, and 100 Granads.</p>
            <p>The 15 the Enemies thought to fill the ditch of the little Sconce, but were hindred of it by ours, where there were ſlaine that night aboue 30 of the Enemies, and of ours were but 2 hurt. On the ſame day it was publiſhed at all corners of the ſtreets, that euery one ſhould break off the Lead which was about their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and to bring it into the Towne-houſe, as alſo from the water and piſsing-places, which the Magiſtrates would begin firſt, and they that did not performe it ſhould forfeit both life and goods.</p>
            <p>The 16 at night ours made a ſalley out with ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lops vpon the Enemies Trenches; where they defea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 2 Sentinels, with ſome Souldiers, one that ſtood a fiſhing had both his leggs ſhot off.</p>
            <p>The 17 we fell out on the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate, vpon the ſtone Bridge, and defeated many of the enemies, we brought alſo in the Towne many armours, and a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeant of theirs.</p>
            <p>The 18 we tooke on the place called <hi>Muntell,</hi> an Enginier, which was about his Workes, and we did cut off both his eares.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:14752:21"/>
The 19 wee skirmiſhed fiercely one againſt another.</p>
            <p>The 20 the Enemies thought to lay a bridge between both the Sconces, with Bauins and Deale boards, which we did ſet on fire with pitch hoopes, and cauſed the Enemies to retire.</p>
            <p>The 21 the Enemies did fall very fiercely vpon the workes of the little Sconce.</p>
            <p>The 22 the Enemies did all their endeuours to get in our Horne-worke, but were forced to retire. And the Ancient <hi>Cornelis Berberts</hi> was killed with a ſhot, which came from the Enemies.</p>
            <p>The 23 early in the morning, the Enemies came twcie vpon our Workes of the Sconce, but were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retyre; they cauſed a Mine to ſpring, but did no hurt, we did kill many with Flayles wherewith the Corne was beaten, we got two that were hurt from the Enemies, which we brought in the Hoſpitall to be cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. The ſame day after dinner, the Enemies came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vpon our Workes, cauſing a Mine to ſpring, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with one of ours, they played thereupon with halfe Courtowes, ſhooting fifteene ſhot vpon ours of the Sconce, there we very fiercely skirmiſhed, and the Captaine <hi>Endenhouldts</hi> went firſt on with his ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, giuing them good courage, whereby he had got great honour, and defeated many men.</p>
            <p>The 24 there was very fiercely ſhot on both ſides, and were throwne in the great Sconce eleuen Granads, which Sconce was very much battered, ſo that the wals were almoſt filled with bullets.</p>
            <p>The 25 Colonell <hi>Baſtocke</hi> was kild vpon the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>workes of the Sconce, who hath at all times carried himſelfe very valiant.</p>
            <p>On the ſame day, and on the 26, the Enemies did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but fill the ditches with wet Bauins of trees, part of which ours fetcht out againe.</p>
            <p>About this time our horſemen did fetch graſſe from
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14752:22"/>the <hi>Doncke,</hi> which ours did dry, and made hey of it in the towne, ſome Burgers hauing the watch on the <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi>-gate, of which ſome were a drinking in the houſe of <hi>Hanſhen Vangenuchten,</hi> where there came a Bullet of an halfe Courtowe through the top, which made a breach that a horſe could haue gone through it, but there was no body hurt.</p>
            <p>The 27 we did nothing elſe but fiercely ſhoot and fight.</p>
            <p>The 28 we did fall out vpon the Enemies Trenches, and vpon their battery, but we found there no Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for that they euery night tooke away the ſame.</p>
            <p>And ours fetcht out of the ditches aboue 300 Bauins. The ſame day we played with our Canon vpon the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Workes, and we heard and ſaw (as the ſpeech went) the ſouldiers of Count <hi>Henry vandenbergh,</hi> vpon the Broome field.</p>
            <p>The 29 ours did ſhoot very fiercely out of the town, and fetcht againe at night about 300 Bauins out of the Ditches of the little Sconce, where were ſlaine two of our Souldiers. The ſame day a womans two legges were ſhot off, and a boyes thumbe.</p>
            <p>The 30 we heard much ſhooting about <hi>Dungen,</hi> by which we vnderſtood that the Kings and Imperiall troopes were neare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whereupon we ſhot very fierely from the towne. At the ſame time there came ouer fiue <hi>Dutch</hi> ſouldiers complaining that in three dayes they had not eaten any bread, and would ſerue the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour.</p>
            <p>Betwixt the 30 and 31, the Enemies fell fiercely vpon the Horne-worke of our Sconce, and played very faſt vpon them, but ours cauſed them to retire, in which were ſlaine a Captaine and a Sergeant of ours.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>July</hi> we got tidings, that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> vpon the <hi>Dungen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> had gotten many priſoners of the Enemies which was eſteemed to be aboue 200 ſouldiers, and 50 Wagons, beſides ſome horſemen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:14752:22"/>
The ſame day the Enemies did ſhoot through the Prieſts Church in the Quire, and alſo in Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> Church in the Organs, but did ſmall hurt.</p>
            <p>The 2 a woman, which was a drawing a Kanne of Beere, was ſhot with a Bullet of a Canon, which tooke away her apron from about her belly, and brake the Kan in pieces, without any more hurt.</p>
            <p>The 3, the Enemies ſhot ouer the Market place, that the Bullet came in a Chamber of the houſe, at the ſigne of the world. Alſo twice through a Mill. At night in the Enemies Leaguer, was an alarme with Drumme beating and ſound of Trumpets, becauſe Count <hi>Henry vanden bergh</hi> prayed very fiercely with Ordnance and Muskets vpon them.</p>
            <p>The 4. there was ſlain a Burger, named <hi>John Hendrixſon</hi> as he was a meaſuring the Prieſts Corne in the Laught, which was the firſt Burger that was killed, the ſecond Burger was called <hi>Yougen Coert,</hi> which the ſame day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the <hi>Orten</hi>-gate, was ſhot in the head.</p>
            <p>The 5 the Enemies threw Granads into the little Sconce, ſo that the Church, being a little Chappell, fell downe. The Enemies were alſo very forward with the filling of the Ditch of the great Sconce.</p>
            <p>The 6 at night 4 of our Land-ſouldiers went out in the enemies Workes, and did ſet on fire ſome Sconce-kornes, becauſe they kept no good Watch. If we had bin ſtrong we had done a notable exploit.</p>
            <p>The 7 (being the <hi>Boſh</hi> Faire) at night we fell out of the towne in the enemies trenches (when they did fill the ditches) ſome of ours were ſlaine, and ſome hurt on both ſides.</p>
            <p>The 8 ours fell on the Enemies workes on the <hi>Hinte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer</hi> gate, where was kild a Captaine, alſo many of the Enemies: from the 8 till the 14 the enemies attempted nothing vpon the Sconces and Towne, but ſhooting and working, thoſe of the Sconce did alſo work againſt
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:14752:23"/>them, and ſeparated the Sconce. About this time two meſſengers went out, to wit, <hi>Iohn Pleyte</hi> and <hi>Awy Awy,</hi> for to try if they could go thorow the Leager; but ſaw no meanes to doe it; ſo they came backe againe.</p>
            <p>The ſame day one of our Ancients (which in a ſalley was taken priſoner) came out of the Leager home a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, with a faire Hat and feather, and a ſiluer Sword: he ſaid that it was giuen him by the Prince, who had alſo made him good cheere. Alſo ours brought in ſome priſoners, being in poore clothes, they were <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotchmen.</hi> The 14 the Kings Corne was ſold to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that would haue it for 18 Gilders the Mett; the Souldiers got Bread, Cheeſe, Beere at the Kings al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance.</p>
            <p>The 15 a pound of Mutton was ſold for 18 ſtiuers.</p>
            <p>The 16 and 17 the enemies ſhot very fiercely vpon the great Sconce, making tryall to take the ſame, but were manfully reſiſted.</p>
            <p>The 18 in the morning at 5 of the Clocke, ours cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Mine to ſpring, &amp; retired then toward the towne; whereupon the Enemies tooke in the ſaid Sconce.</p>
            <p>One of Captaine <hi>Dirck's</hi> ſouldiers being before the Holy Ghoſt, vpon the wall, was ſhot with a Canon in 4 or 5 pieces.</p>
            <p>The ſame day a ſoldier being on the Sconce, was ſhot in the head, that his braines flew out, ſo that he knew not himſelfe, and we could ſee nothing but that he was dead; whereupon his Compagnons that were with him, carried him into the Church-yard, laying him in a Cheſt to bury him; comming there, hee lifted vp his armes and legges, and roſe vp out of the Cheſt, to the great wonder of thoſe that were with him, who carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him into the Hoſpitall, there to be cured. The ſame day, in the <hi>Shilders</hi> ſtreet, a womans head was ſhot off, and a Boy through the body as he ſate a weaning. The ſame euening ours did retire out of the little Sconce to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14752:23"/>to the towne, fearing the enemies would fall vpon them, and for that they were needfull in the towne.</p>
            <p>At night we fell out vpon the Leager of the enemies and defeated 4 Sentinels: and we brought through the Leager two meſſengers, hauing each ſome Pigeons with them, for to bring vs tydings: for that we had not had any Meſſenger in a moneth, becauſe that the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies Sentinels did ſtand very cloſe together, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them ſome water-ſpaniels, which (during the Warres) neuer was ſeene the like.</p>
            <p>The 19 <hi>Marcelis Andreeſen</hi> ſtanding at watch on the <hi>Orten-gate,</hi> had one of his legs ſhot off: the ſame day there came two Drummers, hauing with them ſome pickled Herrings to diſtribute amongſt their Friends.</p>
            <p>The 20 the Enemies did ſhoot very fiercely thorow <hi>S. Johns</hi> Church, and vpon the rowne.</p>
            <p>The 21 there came againe into the towne 2 Drum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers to releaſe ſome priſoners, who had againe ſome pickled Herrings for to giue away: they tooke with them many Horſes which wee had taken from them, and were ſold amongſt the Enemies, becauſe we had no food for them: the ſame Drummers brought ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings, that in the Leager, ſome meſſengers that were ſent by Count <hi>Henry vanden bergh</hi> towards the towne, were to ſuffer death. The old pickled Herrings were for 4, 5, and 6 ſtiuers a peece; Beefe for 9 and 10 ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers a pound; a buſhell of Turneps (which before the ſiege was ſold for a ſtiuer) was ſold for 5, 6, and 9 ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers.</p>
            <p>At that ſame day there came ſome other Drummers, which alſo brought ſome Limons and Herrings to giue away.</p>
            <p>The 22 the Conſtable, <hi>Hans den ouden Clerk's</hi> Head was ſhot of. On the ſame night there came a Enginier vpon the <hi>Doncke,</hi> before S. <hi>Johns</hi> Gate, for
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14752:24"/>to meaſure ſomething, the which our Soldiers got and brought in, and was in great danger to loſe his life. At that time the enemies ſhot fiercely with Ordnance.</p>
            <p>The 23 the Burgers on the <hi>Orten-gate</hi> ſhot fiercely vpon the Enemies. This day the Magiſtrates denyed (for the firſt time) Gunpowder amongſt the Burgers. And one called <hi>Groen,</hi> ſitting talking before his doore, had one of his legs ſhot off.</p>
            <p>The 24, from the <hi>Hintemer</hi> gate, and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter-gate,</hi> were ſhot by ours aboue 300 ſhot vpon the Enemies.</p>
            <p>The 25. (on S. <hi>Iames</hi> day) our Souldiers brought in 7 Boores, and a Boy, which they had fetcht neere vnder the Enemies quarters; if the Boy had not cryed, they would haue gotten a Waggon with women, who were come to ſee. This night departed many Companies of the Enemies, and ours were in their <hi>Cops de guardes,</hi> where they found no body. They brought a ſhallop full of Wheele-barrowes, Shouels, Deales, and Wood.</p>
            <p>The 26 the Burgers watches were altered out of the Gates, they were now commanded to goe vpon the ſteeples on the walles of the Towne. The ſame day the Enemies made a great falley vpon our Halfe-Moone; where there were ſlaine many of them, and 7 of ours, with 10 hurt: yet we were forced to leaue the fame.</p>
            <p>The 27 our ſouldiers fell out, and brought in againe ſome Wheelbarrowes and other things, with ſome pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners and Horſes: but the Gouernour commanded that wee ſhould bring in no more Horſes, becauſe wee had no food for them within the Towne.</p>
            <p>The 28 a Bakers man comming at night homewards, going to bed, fell from the Chamber, who roſe vp, and went againe to the Chamber, and to bed, who in the morning was found dead, and buried the next day: the Clarke hearing the dead ſighing, called ſome men, and there came preſently by hundreds together, to open the Graue, to fetch the man out; a Batchelor tooke him by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:14752:24"/>the hand, and drew him out of the Cheſt, but hee was dead, and remained dead; his cheekes were very red, and the blood ran out of his mouth, which many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men did ſee; whereupon the whole towne was in alteration. On this day freſh butter was ſold one Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a pound, and ſalt butter 30 ſtiuers, a couple of yong Pigeons for 24 ſtiuers, a Pullet a rixdoller, a pound of Mutton 20 and 24 ſtiuers, candles 12 ſtiuers a pound, an Egge two blancks.</p>
            <p>The 29 and 30 the enemies ſhot with Arrowes, ſuch as we ſhoot with Bowes. This day the Sho omakers and Lether-ſellors did dry their Hides, becauſe there was no tallow to be gotten: the Tallow of the beaſts was ſold for 12 ſtiuers a pound, which we melted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with oyle of Turneps, to be eaten vpon bread: Alſo Muſtard was mingled with oyle of Turneps, to be eaten with bread: the Horſes which were brought in, did eat the leaues of the trees, and the Conſtables did beat them from the walls into the ditches of the town; thoſe that could not ſwim ouer, were drowned.</p>
            <p>The laſt day of the ſame moneth the Enemies ſhot in pieces on of the Mills.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the Enemies ſhot very fiercely with Cannon and Muskets vpon the Towne; and the Burgers did much wonder that the Souldiers did keep watch in the Fiſh-market, S. <hi>Iohns,</hi> and the <hi>Orten</hi>-gates<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which were the beſt Watches</p>
            <p>The 2 the Enemies did a manfull ſalley on the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terſcarp before the <hi>Vuchter-gate,</hi> but were forced to retire, with great loſſe of theirs, and 4 of our s. The ſame day a childs head was ſhot off, and a womans legge. At this time the Eccleſiaſticall perſons, as <hi>Paters</hi> of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites prieſts, Friers S. <hi>Iohns</hi> Monkes, Baſelers, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, did all together make vp two Counterſcarps or workes, behinde the Siſtets of <hi>Orten.</hi> We got alſo ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings that the Imperialiſts were come into the <hi>Betuwe,</hi>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:14752:25"/>and that they had taken <hi>Reuen,</hi> and <hi>Wagemingen,</hi> but we afterwards vnderſtood the contrary.</p>
            <p>The 4 the enemies ſhot two ſhots neere the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſteeple, ſo that a Mill fell downe. The ſame day the Enemies made a ſalley vpon the foremoſt Workes, on the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter-gate,</hi> with about 500 <hi>Frenchmen,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which were many Gentiles and Voluntiers: there were ſlaine many of them, and they were forced to retire. The Enomies ſhot many Granads vpon the <hi>Molen-brugger-wall,</hi> ſo that euery one did retire from thence farther into the Towne.</p>
            <p>The 5 the Enemies cauſed a Mine to ſpring, and they fell in the fore-worke, but were forced with the loſſe of ſome Souldiers and Voluntiers, to retire backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The ſame day the enemies did ſend for their ſlaine &amp; hurt men, among which were many Gentiles.</p>
            <p>The 6 there was much ſhooting on both ſides, vpon and out of our foreworke. The Enemies killed with a ſhot from the <hi>Donck,</hi> 5 men on the <hi>Vuchter-gaete,</hi> and ſome loſt their armes and legges: there were ſo many Granads ſhot into the towne, that the people were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to retire deeper into the towne, and were much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid: the Enemies fetcht the earth with whole Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets from the fore-worke, and beſides approached ſtill.</p>
            <p>The 7 the Captaine <hi>Campagne</hi> commanded a great many priſoners of the Enemies to goe to the <hi>Donck,</hi> with the which he ran ouer vnto the Enemies; with this <hi>Campagne</hi> lodged alwaies the Drummers, and hee knew all that which paſſed by the Gouernour in the towne, which we doe not doubt, but that he hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſeſted it vnto the Prince: they ſhot ſo fiercely with Granads, that we did not reſpect the ſhooting of the Ordnance: and there were daily ſlaine ſo many men, that I leaue to ſet downe the number.</p>
            <p>The 8 the Enemies came into our foreworke, which we left to ſaue our Souldiers, becauſe there were daily
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14752:25"/>many killed. The ſame day the Gouernour and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, cauſed the Burgers to be aſſembled, propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchteren</hi> wall ſhould be entrenched, and the houſes puld downe, vnto which the Burgers were vnwilling, ſaying; if we could not hold the Sconces and out-workes, and if our walles of the towne cannot reſiſt, what ſhall it be when our houſes are broken downe, and we looſe our grounds. And they ſaid alſo, you haue broken downe (without our conſent) the Wind-milles, you may alſo doe this if it doe like you.</p>
            <p>The 9, there was offered by the Gouernour and Magiſtrates, that whatſoeuer Burgers or voluntaries would goe with the ſouldiers in the Trenches, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the Enemies, that they may doe it freely, whereupon ſome ſaid, if we doe it, it is more then reaſon that wee ſhould receiue the Kings money and bread.</p>
            <p>The 10 and 11 the Enemies ſhot many Granads, which cauſed great pitifull cryings and dammage.</p>
            <p>The 11 the Gouernours and the Magiſtrates cauſed the Burgers againe to be aſſembled, propounding that it was certaine that Captaine <hi>Compagne</hi> had manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted vnto the Enemies the ſtate of the towne, and that there ſhould be choſen Commiſsioners, ſome out of the Clergy, ſome out of the Councell of Warre, the third from among the Burgers, what they would ordaine to make and to breake, that ſame ſhould be accompliſhed, vnto which the Burgers would not condiſcend; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Gouernours and Magiſtrates required of them, that they would ſubſcribe an Act, that they could not coudeſcend vnto the cutting off, of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchteren</hi> wall, nor alſo would not goe to the Trenches, of which there was nothing done. The Clergie was alſo aſſembled for to furniſh money for the payment of the ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>The 12 the Enemies ſhot very fircely with Granads, of which one fell in the <hi>Croſſe-brothers-Church;</hi> the which deſtroyed all the ſeates, and all the Glaſſes in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14752:26"/>ſame Church. A Monke of about 80 yeeres of age, was cruſhed in pieces, ſo that there was found nothing but one of his legges, and a piece of his head. This day there went three Meſſengers out of the towne, from w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> the Pigeons did returne. The ſame day there were buried in the towne two <hi>French</hi> Counts: the one did ſerue the King, and the other the States.</p>
            <p>The 13 there was very fiercely ſhot, and at night were ſent into the towne 11 Granads, which did great hurt to the houſes and men, ſo that euery one was in feare: the ſame day the Gouernour and Preſident aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled with the Lord Biſhop, to what end, is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the Burgers: whereupon followed, that at night there went out about one thouſand men, for to cut through a damme, but could not be brought to the effect. They brought in ſome priſoners, and killed ſome; This night the Granads did much hurt to the men and houſes.</p>
            <p>The 14 in the morning the Enemies ſhot very fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly into the towne with Grenads, that it was very la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable to ſee, and rained ſome houſes; of ſome the heaues and tops were damunified very much.</p>
            <p>The 15 the Enemies plaid very fiercely with their Canon.</p>
            <p>The 16 the Enemies ſhot aboue 300 ſhot vpon the <hi>Vuchter</hi> gate and ſtreet, and about 25 Granads, ſo that the people could not goe quietly in the ſtreets; the <hi>Croſſe-Brothers</hi> were faine to retire out of the Cloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and went by the Fryers to dwell, and to doe their ſeruice. We got this day good tidings, whereupon was commanded vnto the watches to let flye all their Ancients as well vpon the gates, as the walles, for a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken that we yet were well minded and couragious.</p>
            <p>The 17 the Enemies did nothing elſe but ſhoot with Ordnance, and threw 20 Granads in the towne.</p>
            <p>The 18 the Enemies brought many Bauins for to fill
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14752:26"/>the ditch. They did alſo a ſally vpon our Workes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Graefse</hi>-gate, which did endure from about 11 of the clock at noone, vntill 6 of the clocke at night, where there were ſlaine and hurt many on both ſides; Alſo there were ſome vpon the walles, but were forced to retire.</p>
            <p>The 19 there were ſent 5 Granads vpon the <hi>Vuchte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren</hi>-wall, and then it was very quiet, but were brought neere the towne about 50 Wagons with Bauins, they ſhot but with three pieces of Ordnance, though at night againe with Granads, ſo that the dead men which were buried, were digged out of their graues.</p>
            <p>The 20 the Enemies ſhot very fiercely vpon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchter</hi>-gate and the Bulworke, that there fell great breaches out of the ſaid bulworke in the ditches; Alſo ſome Sconce-kornes fell downe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſame day aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Gouernour, Preſident, and the Captaines of the Burgers, with the Lord Biſhop, but to what end re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth ſecret. This day the Enemies did a ſally vpon the Works without the <hi>Graefse</hi>-gate, where they were beaten backe, and many men were ſlaine and hurt.</p>
            <p>The 21 the Enemies did againe a ſally vpon the ſaid Worke, which ours were forced to leaue.</p>
            <p>The 22 the ſouldiers of the Captaine <hi>Dirck de leeue,</hi> brought in three horſes, with a Cornet, which they tooke priſoner (as they ſay) from <hi>Wyckde duerſten,</hi> by whom we vnderſtood that Count <hi>Henry vander bergh</hi> had taken <hi>Amersfort,</hi> and three dayes after pillaged it, and left it. Alſo that the Enemies had taken with an enterpriſe the towne of <hi>Weſell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 23 the Enemies ſhot againe very fiercely with Canon, but no more with Granads, whereof wee were glad: the Gouernours and Magiſtrates did ordaine; that the Burgers in the morning and after dinner, ſhould worke three houres. At night the Enemies did make Bone fires, and ioyfull tokens for the taking of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14752:27"/>
               <hi>Weſell,</hi> they plaid alſo with Ordnance and Muskets that neuer was ſeene the like.</p>
            <p>The 24 the Enemies did come very neere with their approaches.</p>
            <p>The 25 the Enemies ſhot with granads vpon the fiſh-market, ſo that euery one did put their houſhold-ſtuffe into the ſellors, and themſelues went deeper in the towne.</p>
            <p>The 26 the Enemies did fill a part of the Ditches of the towne, and approached euery day very much, they threw with Granads, by which was ſet an houſe on fire, vpon the which they ſhot very fiercely, by which meanes many Burgers and ſouldiers were ſlaine: there came tidings that the Enemies had taken <hi>Santvliet,</hi> but was not true.</p>
            <p>The 27 in the morning betimes, two poſts were ſent to <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> which tooke with them pigeons; we had not had in 7 weeks any tydings nor Meſſengers: this day ours brought in the <hi>Droſſart</hi> of <hi>Gorcums-man,</hi> with a braue horſe, who ſaid that Gount <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw</hi> was with 16000 men about <hi>Endhouen,</hi> and that it was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended vpon <hi>Heuſden.</hi> This day the Enemies were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much buſie to fill the ditches, and ſhot very fiercely vpon Saint <hi>Iohns</hi> ſteeple, and with granads in the <hi>Hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temer</hi> ſtreet, which cauſed great hurt on men and houſes.</p>
            <p>The 29 the Enemies began againe to ſhoot with granads, ſpecially vpon the Prieſts Cloiſter, where were ſome houſes altogether deſtroyed: this day there came a pigean in the towne, which was a token that the ſaid Poſts were come through the Leaguer, and out of dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger. The ſame day the Gouernour and Magiſtrates did command that the <hi>Vuchteren</hi> wall ſhould be cut off; and the Magiſtrates gaue Beere vnto the Pyoners: the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours diuided alſo muition bread amongſt the nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Burgers, if the towne ſhould be releeued, that then
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14752:27"/>they ſhould pay it againe within halfe a yeere; if not, they ſhould not pay for it. There was alſo ſold Oyle, Stock-fiſh, Ryſe, and other victuals, that were bought for the Garriſon, this was done for to get money. The Oyle was ſold for 25 ſtiuers the Kanne, a pound of Ryſe 4 ſtiuers, Stockfiſh 4 ½ ſtiuer a pound.</p>
            <p>The 30 the Enemies were buſie to fill vp the ditches with Bauens; of which we ſet ſome on fire. The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies were ſo bold, that ſome looked ouer the Walles, which came not well to paſſe for them.</p>
            <p>The 31 we began to loſe our courage, ſome Burgers refuſed to watch, and others to worke; thereupon the Magiſtrates co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded that the Burgers ſhould watch of two nights one: and vnto thoſe that did worke was giuen Beere, Bread, and Cheeſe, for that they ſhould be the more willing.</p>
            <p>The firſt of <hi>September</hi> there roſe great alteration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Burgers who dwelled vpon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>uchteren</hi> wall, becauſe there was giuen order to make a Ditch on the <hi>Orchen,</hi> and through a Field behinde <hi>Iacob Gyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brechts,</hi> in that manner to cut thorow the ſaid Wall; whereupon the Burgers (being 20 or 30 in number) went to the Preſident <hi>Henry Franſen van geſſell,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining vnto him of the ſame, who gaue them for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Beate them away if they be there.</p>
            <p>The 2 the ſame perſons went into the Town-houſe, where they got no contentment according to their minde, returning homewards, ſaid, There lye our Armes, we will not watch, but keepe our Houſes and <hi>Vuchteren</hi> Wall, which was of more importance then their watching or working.</p>
            <p>The Enemies ſhot ſo fiercely vpon the <hi>Coc</hi>-wall with Ordnance and Granads, that many houſes were throwne downe: there came alſo a bullet thorow S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iohns</hi> Church, which damnified the whole Organs in our Ladies Quire.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:14752:28"/>
The 4 the Enemies ſhot ſo many Granads vpon the <hi>Vuchteren</hi> wall, that no body could keepe him there for feare of being hurt; the like was euery where in the towne.</p>
            <p>The Enemies came with their Galleries neere our out-workes, which we haue before the <hi>Vuchter-gate,</hi> ouer the ditch into our Bulwarkes.</p>
            <p>The 5, 6, 7, and following dayes, the iealouſie of the Burgers did more and more increaſe againſt the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, his brother-in-law, and the Preſident; Many ſaid publikely, We were commanded to prouide our houſes vpon great penalties, and now there is no Powder; We haue many yeeres brought vp Fortification mony and Subſidies, for to fortifie the Walls and towne, now we are well ſerued, we haue a rich Gouernour, a rich Preſident, &amp;c, the which haue cozened vs very much, and ſuch like iniurious words; whereupon followed, that vpon the 9 and 10 the Enemies tooke in the halfe-moone before the <hi>Vuchter-gate,</hi> and ours were retired into the Towne.</p>
            <p>The 11 in the morning, there ſprung a Mine in the great Bulwarke, which did make ſuch an alteration a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Burgers, that each cryed for to parly: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſome were committed, and a great many of the Burgers ran vpon the Walls, putting off their Hats, and ſo the compoſition was agreed vpon, and ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed on the 14, and the Gouernour, with the Garriſon, and many Eccleſiaſticall perſons, and ſome Burgers, marched out of the Towne on the 17: whereupon there was in the towne great heauineſſe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14752:28"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
